howdy hey any secrets you want to tell
us oh that got me two and a half years
in prison I should probably keep my
mouth shut
[Music]
what's life like as a spy Oh Jared it
was so much fun I miss it very much
actually I got to see the world 65
countries recruited nine spies over the
years to work for us it was fun well
let's get this part of this story out of
the way you were actually my high school
teacher I was American government in
American history I do remember you
because every once in a while there's a
teacher who stands out who actually for
some reason or another gets you to pay
attention to listen so thank you for
that thank you
that's very kind of you it's insane man
this is a pretty weird world to go from
high school teacher to international spy
Jared life takes these very odd twists
and turns
you just never know what's in store for
you that last semester that I had you in
class I went to see the professor and he
said listen I ought to tell you I'm not
really a professor here I'm actually
undercover as a professor I'm a senior
CIA officer would you be interested in
joining the CIA and I said sure hadn't
really thought of it but I was getting
married soon after graduation I had no
job and I thought well this sounds like
fun so next thing I know a few months
later I was in the CIA when I first
arrived somebody met me at the front
gate and they took me into an auditorium
with about 30 other people and I raised
my right hand and I swore to uphold the
Constitution I didn't swear to to you
know keep the agency's crimes a secret
but I swore to uphold the Constitution
and I meant it and they put me to work
on Iraq and they said the reason I was
being assigned to Iraq was that nothing
ever happened
so I had been there about nine months
and just as I begin to feel like I
really know what I'm talking about Iraq
invades Kuwait so next thing I know I'm
I'm going to the White House and
briefing the president and taking a call
at my desk from Colin Powell when he was
the national security adviser and then I
went into Kuwait City with the Marines
on Liberation Day March 1st 1991 I went
through the whole traditional
clandestine operations training guns
explosives counterterrorism driving
jumping out of an airplane swimming
through a swamp to you know make a dead
drop on an island you're all covered
with leeches you have to fight the
cottonmouths that are swimming across
the the bog it was it was rough but one
thing that I was really really good at
was convincing people to commit treason
now oftentimes they'll want money but a
lot of times it's not about the money
they want their children to go to an
American University one guy wanted a new
Vespa I mean he was willing to commit
treason for me espionage in exchange for
a Vespa one guy did it just because he
loved the United States so what happened
after that in the summer of 2000 there
was an attempt on my life in Athens
there was a terrorist group there they
planned to kill me on the way to work
one day but they saw that I was in an
armored car and they knew from earlier
surveillance that I was carrying a
weapon and so instead they killed my
next-door neighbor Stephen Saunders who
was the British defense attache so I was
deemed to be a little bit too hot
meaning too many of our enemies knew my
true identity and so I was pulled back
from the Middle East and then September
11th hit
[Applause]
it was in Pakistan as the chief of
counterterrorism operations that I led
what became the biggest counterterrorism
raid in CIA's history we captured Abu
Zubaydah who we believed at the time was
the number three in al-qaeda we picked
him up and we threw him into the back of
a filthy Toyota pickup truck and then he
went to what ended up being the first
CIA secret prison where is he now he's
in Guantanamo now he's been in CIA
custody for almost 14 years now he's not
been charged with a crime
Elad what are they waiting for they
can't legally charge him with a crime
because everything that he ever told the
CIA was as a result of torture they
began with the most entry level of the
torture techniques they would grab him
by the lapels and shove him up against a
plywood wall and all that stuff is
humiliating but it's not painful in any
way but then things get very serious
very quickly after that Abu Zubaydah for
example had an irrational fear of
cockroaches and so they would keep him
in a dog cage and they would fill the
cage with cockroaches just to make him
insane they ended up waterboarding him
83 times and even after 83 times he gave
up no actionable intelligence he saved
no American lives he disrupted no
attacks against the United States the
torture just simply doesn't work and so
it was it was a crime with no outcome
that you can show the American people
actually helped anybody
there were techniques to Jared that I
that I thought were worse than
waterboarding there was something called
the cold cell where we strip a prisoner
naked you chained him to an eyebolt in
the ceiling so his arms are up and he
can't get comfortable
he can't kneel or sit or lay down his
cell is chilled to 50 degrees and every
hour somebody goes in and throws ice
water on him that's illegal
we killed three people using that
technique but no one was ever charged
with a crime I mean the investigation
found that yep he died well sorry too
bad was an accident
we can't lose who we are as Americans in
the name of counterterrorism you know we
have civil liberties in this country and
I want my September 10th country back I
left the CIA in 2004 I went into the
private sector and I kept my mouth shut
for five and a half years and in 2007 I
got a call from Brian Ross at ABC News
so I went down to the ABC News studio in
Washington Brian Ross flew in from New
York and I said three things in that
interview that utterly changed the
course of the rest of my life I said the
CIA was torturing its prisoners I said
that torture was official US government
policy and I said the policy was
approved by and signed by the President
of the United States the CIA was very
angry with me for airing the dirty
laundry and so they asked the Justice
Department to to charge me in January of
2012 I was charged with three counts of
espionage for the ABC News interview now
the point really was not to find me
guilty the point was to make an example
of me to deter other whistleblowers from
coming forward and the Justice
Department really has this down to a
science
they know that your attorneys are very
expensive I had 11 attorneys but I was
looking at 45 years in prison
I said I'm not doing 45 minutes I'm
gonna fight this I don't care what it
costs that's not really what your
defense attorneys wanting here and you
know we got up over a million bucks and
they said look I think we should
investigate the idea of a plea and they
said well what do you want us to offer
them I said tell him I'll do a year in a
day a year in a day would make me
eligible for early release at ten and a
half months so we offered a year in a
day and they came back with three years
we went with two they said two and a
half and they said it's our final offer
so what do you do I have five kids at
home do you roll the dice knowing that
the government wins ninety eight point
two percent of its cases according to
Pro Publica I couldn't take that chance
so I took the deal and then just a
couple of months later my attorneys
drove me up to prison and dropped me off
[Music]
anything that keeps you up at night I'm
not sure that we can trust our
government everything that the CIA has
told us since 2001 has been a lie and it
doesn't matter who's in the White House
in August of this year 2015 the White
House killed 424 people in August these
are people who've never been charged
with a crime they've never faced their
accusers in court they've never had
their day to explain themselves we're
supposed to take the CIA's word for it
that these are bad people but then we
have these independent voices Human
Rights Watch Amnesty International the
International Committee of the Red Cross
saying wait a minute 90% of these people
are innocent civilians who just happened
to be near the site of these drone
attacks one of my attorneys is
representing a drone whistleblower right
now and he told me recently that he was
operating his drone from a base in I
think it was Nevada or New Mexico
he's connected by radio and the guy in
CENTCOM says you see the target launch
and the guy said I can't launch there's
a child next to him
and the guy at CENTCOM said it's not a
child it's a goat and he said man I'm
looking at it it's a child and he told
him launch but the guy said and I
couldn't launch that thing and he didn't
well now he's facing court-martial and
possibly other charges including a
dishonorable discharge for refusing to
kill a child I mean is this really where
we want our country to be have we so
turned our backs on civil liberties
since September 11th in the name of
national security it was a child where
Americans were better than that and it's
not too late to turn this thing around
ed Snowden opened so many doors for
people around the world to discuss these
issues that courage is just so rare and
so special he risked everything and
because he did it in such a public
fashion the big guns were pulled out
against him
and I told him don't come home I said
you won't get a fair trial in the
Eastern District of Virginia your jury
will be made up of people from the CIA
FBI DoD Homeland Security and every
intelligence and defense contractor in
Washington I said don't come home not
until the American people come to their
senses and realize what a national
service you've provided what's the worst
case scenario the worst case scenario is
that the courts uphold the ability of
NSA to keep spying on American citizens
and that NSA continues to build
facilities like the new one they have in
Utah that has enough storage space to
record and hold every telephone call
text message and email from every
American citizen for the next five
hundred years and that the American
people don't realize what we're losing
here in terms of our civil liberties you
know there there are no demonstrations
in the street and I just don't
understand why that is so the worst case
scenario really is that the American
people don't come to their senses in
time to save the country
[Music]
you